What's up, Dolph fans? We are here with
the team that's building the team in the
2026 NFL draft. Miami Dolphins, 11 picks
this year. Cannot wait for it all and I
cannot wait to talk to my next guest
here, Kyle Smith, the assistant GM of
your Miami Dolphins. Kyle, how you
doing, man?
>> Good, good. Appreciate you.
>> Very happy to have you on here. Just
first, how's it going getting your
bearings in South Florida? How's your
transition going to the new job here in
Miami?
>> It's been good. It's been really smooth.
I'm still in a hotel, be locked up in a
hotel for uh until after the draft. But
um it's it really in short order since
coming in here, you can find out right
away that this is a first class
organization. You know, all the way
across the board, football operations,
equipment staff, field staff, food, the
food's been outstanding. Um you know,
everyone talks about one of the first
things they talk about when they get in
here and and and I believe it. But uh
it's been it's been great.
>> Just wait till night one of the draft
the spread they get out there. Yeah, I
can't wait every morning for uh for
breakfast, man. That's the best meal in
my opinion. No doubt they they knock it
out. The eggs benedict and the and the
French toast today was
>> whatever they put out there today.
>> It was off the charts. So, take us more
into kind of that process because
obviously you're kind of getting your
feet wet and getting your bearings here,
but also the job is so wide ranging for
an assistant GM. Can you just kind of
take us through what some of your main
duties are here at the Dolphins? Yeah,
I'd say the, you know, obviously it's
both sides, pro and college, you know,
scouting and kind of overseeing both
departments, but the main job for me is
to create clarity, you know, for John
Eric and and and halfway in the decision
makers. Um, you know, obviously right
now we're we're, you know, right in the
midst of the draft preparation. Um, but
even before that it was, you know, free
agency and it's going through thorough,
you know, process and meetings and, uh,
grinding through everything and and
we've got a really good staff and, uh,
scouts, both pro and college. So, uh,
that's really the main job is obviously
the evaluations, overseeing both
departments and doing everything you can
to to create clarity for decision
makers.
>> Yeah, it makes perfect sense. Can you
take us kind of into the the
relationship with John Eric and yourself
because obviously he's spoken very
highly of you. I'm sure you've he's
talked about you being a future GM in
this league. Just uh how how has that
relationship developed from where it was
when it first started and to where it is
now?
>> Yeah, it's we go back a long ways. We
kind of, you know, he's been in it a
little bit longer than I have, you know,
but we kind of cut our teeth together on
the road as area scouts. And the way
that it works is as scouts. He obviously
was with the Packers. I was with, you
know, Washington um at first. And you
work with other scouts more than you
work with your own scouts because you're
out on the road with them. And so we
developed a relationship back then. We
went to from Southwest to Southeast,
kept in contact. You always kind of
surround yourself with guys that kind of
think the same, work the same. We've
always shared the same vision. We've
always talked about these moments. If
one were to get a GM job and the other
one's coming with you, um, and and it
just so happened to line up for us. So,
um, he's a tremendous person. Uh, you
know, obviously a really good scout and
and an evaluator and, uh, couldn't be
happier to be here with him. I imagine
some of that time on the road provides a
lot of value for what the job is now,
right? In terms of delegating and
working with the staff under you.
>> Yeah, I think I think being, you know,
anytime you're in personnel, it's, you
know, the guys that are working for you,
with you, you know, when you've been
there and done that and and you're never
going to ask guys to do something that
you haven't done. And and that's a big
emphasis from from J and myself. It's,
you know, we're never going to ask guys
to do stuff that that we haven't done at
any point. And and, you know, I think
that's a big part of it. That's a great
managerial tool to have right there for
sure. And being in the ind industry for
so long, I'm sure you've learned a lot
of different things about aspects of the
job. What are some of the key things you
picked up along the way that you hope to
bring here to the Dolphins?
>> Yeah, you know, there's there's so many
I think sometimes it's it's we try to
keep things simple, you know, and and
it's take good football players. I know
that sounds like obvious statement, but
it is. There's a lot of different
information that goes into we're a best
player available team and that's how
that's how we'll operate. I know John
Eric has talked about that, but you
know, there's so much information that
goes into either signing a player in
free agency or picking a player in the
draft. You have all different avenues
and and and data and information and the
scouts opinions and and coaches opinions
and everything. When it boils down to
it, you're looking for that alignment um
that everybody in the building sees it
the same. Your convictions, do they have
the character traits that we look for
and do the is the skill set match what
we look for? and and you pick the best
player that's that's staring at you on
the board.
>> You talk about that shared aesthetic,
right, in terms of getting guys on the
same page. How do you go about
developing that as a staff? Like
obviously you and John Eric have a big
hand in that, but how do you kind of get
everyone aligned in terms of this is
what we want it to look like and we need
to all see it kind of similarly.
>> Yeah, you try to have a you know
everybody you want everyone's individual
opinions. You don't want group you want
group think to a point to have the
shared vision u but you want individual
opinions on the player. You don't want
everybody to see it the same. Um, but
when you bring, you know, the coaches
in, when you bring scouts in, everybody
who's who's talking about the individual
player, um, they're the most important
person in the room at that point. Um,
and you take everybody's information
that they have and you try to do the
best you can to to collectively come
together with that that shared vision.
>> Yeah, it makes a lot of sense. And, you
know, part of that is is building the
draft board, right? That's one of those
things where I'm sure it starts with a
massive collection of names back in in
in the summer and August and now you
kind of whittle it down and and one of
the questions I was most excited for
anybody in this entire process was the
lore behind building that draft board. I
was hoping you can give us a bit of a
look behind the scenes in terms of how
that comes together from where it was
back in August to where it comes now
here coming up with the draft.
>> Yeah, I mean it's it's obviously it's
very long process, thorough process, but
this is when it it really gets fun, you
know, is this time of year. But, you
know, it really starts in the summer
before we show up at training camp. you
know, in terms of the draft, you know,
the the area scouts are the first boots
on the ground. They put grades on guys
and they go through the fall visits and
then we have our February meetings.
February meetings, it's really their
time. The area scouts, the cross
checkers to set that board, give their
opinion, you know, the profile of the
player. They've talked to everybody at
every school call about the guy. Um, and
then obviously as the baton kind of gets
passed and then we got all-star games
and then we get the combine and then
here come the coaches. So there's all
different layers to the massaging of
that board up down as you get more
information and as the clarity starts to
build.
>> And by the time you turn the card in and
I get here, you probably feel like you
know the young man pretty well.
>> Oh yeah, there's no doubt about it. I
mean, you know, there's you've gone over
him so shoot, we just walked out of the
the meeting right now and you've gone
over these guys so much and but that's
that's why you do it. It's there there
always comes a moment of clarity and
that's what I think is the best part of
our job or the most gratifying is is it
could be in fall visit you might have
that clarity of this is the guy he's not
moving from the board at this point and
and it stays that way all the way
through or there's guys that it takes a
little bit of time you got to get the
all-star games you got to get the
combine you got to get a coach's vision
but at some point or you're at the
proday live and you're looking at the
guy move around and you find the clarity
some point that clarity comes and that's
what we're searching for and by draft
night we'll have clarity on every one of
those guys.
>> That's why draft season is 365 days a
year as I always say on my podcast. So
you talk about collaboration with the
scouting staff. I I one of my favorite
kind of uh threads to weave is is the
collaboration between you guys and the
coaching staff because you know
sometimes coaches maybe want more of a
football player. Sometimes maybe the
scouting staff wants to trace, right?
You have to find a way to marry that
together. Just talk about the ideal
collaboration between scouting staff and
coaching staff if you can. I I think
that's extremely important, you know,
because there comes a certain point in
the draft or in free agency depending on
the money that you're paying a player.
Uh there's a layer in the draft whether
that could be second round one year, it
could be fourth round and below the next
year, you know, it just varies uh based
on the year, but there comes a point
where there aren't the players that are
they can do it all. They might be really
good at one thing and not so good at the
other and need development in another
aspect. Well, we need the coaches to
help us find that vision of how they're
going to use this player and and what
can we develop because there are
everyone's flawed. We're all flawed and
so are the players. So, we got to know
the vision from the coaches. Are they
going to be put into certain positions
to, you know, extenduate their their
strengths and not their weaknesses. So,
the vision of how the players going to
be used um is extremely important.
>> It's more like we're not drafting a guy
for Huya today, but who's going to be
>> Yes. you're always always thinking about
year one, but but we're never, you know,
discounting down the road and what he's
going to be, you know, at the end of his
contract.
>> Yeah, it makes perfect sense. So, we
talked a lot about uh John Eric Sullivan
and your relationship, but how about
some other mentors you've come across in
your time in the NFL that have really
had a profound impact on you in this
job?
>> Yeah, I've been fortunate to, you know,
I've been around some really, you know,
elite football people uh throughout my
career. My my dad obviously AJ Smith was
a general manager for 10 years in the
Chargers, alltime winning as GM in
Charger history. So I I was born and
raised in the personnel side. John Eric
was born and raised in the in the
coaching side obviously with his dad
being an elite coach. Um but even so a
lot of my what I believe in the pillars,
your foundations come from him. Um he
was with the Buffalo Bills and learned
under Bill Poland the Hall of Famer. Um,
and then when I got to the league, I
started in Washington. Mike Shanahan,
Kyle, you know, the tree that that's
talked about all the time. Kyle Shanahan
floor, all those guys. Um, they were on
the coaching side. I was on the
personnel side. But to learn under and
watch Mike Shanahan, coach, you know,
was was unbelievable. And still some of
the things that he would say, you you
you carry on as you as you go through
the process. Um, but I would I've been
fortunate to be around a lot of really
talented football minds. I get the sense
that maybe in first grade when your
teacher asked you to write what you want
to be when you grow up, you might have
said something about being in football.
>> Yes. Yeah. No, I thought I was going to
be a player for a long time and then
when I found out I wasn't good enough,
you know, then it was definitely, you
know, following my dad's footsteps.
>> What's the What's your favorite part of
a job?
>> I, you know, there there's so much like
this time of year like February meetings
and on is really that's probably my
favorite part of the job. it. The
favorite like moments are what we were
just talking about earlier, that clarity
when when you find that clarity of,
okay, this guy's going here on the board
and he's staying there and that's where
it is and you're hoping that it falls a
certain way. But it's the it's finding
that clarity because it's not it's not
hard. It's or it's not easy, I should
say. You know, there there's times that
you need the full process to go through
guys and you're trying to figure them
out. Um, but you always come up with
that moment of clarity and and that's
what I that's what I love about it. the
satisfaction of the culmination of all
the work kind of crystallizing there. No
doubt.
>> Let's conclude with this. We have seven
picks in the top 100 this year, 11
overall. I can't wait for it.
Personally, I'm sure you guys feel the
same way. What are you most excited
about for this year's draft?
>> I mean, just just adding. I mean, it's,
you know, it's we're going to get good
football players at every level. It's
not just the, you know, the number.
Obviously, the number more picks you
have, the more shots you have on target
and on goal, as they say, more chances
you have to hit. But um you know that
doesn't necessarily mean that we're
going to have 11. We got 11 going in, we
might have less. Maybe we trade up and
and do all those things or we gather
more for for next year. So there's a lot
of different you got a lot of
flexibility when you have that kind of
capital. But um there's definitely uh
we're excited about the draft. We're
excited about the volume um and how we
can impact the team not only this year
but as we talked about earlier moving
forward.
>> A lot that can happen for your Miami
Dolphins come draft weekend. He's
assistant general manager Kyle Smith.
Kyle, we appreciate your time today,
man. Thank you.
>> Thanks. Thanks, man.